<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian sacrifice by Iames Barker ...</title>
            <author>Barker, James, fl. 1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848573</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848573</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 641:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian sacrifice by Iames Barker ...</title>
                  <author>Barker, James, fl. 1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 148 [i.e. 152], [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphry Blunden neare ye Rroyall [sic] Exchange in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630 [i.e. 1639]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved title page.</note>
                  <note>Publication date on title page erroneous; actual publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>A treatise on Pro. 23:26.</note>
                  <note>Pages 110-11 transposed in numbering; 144 repeated in number, and erroneous numbering continues; 152, final numbered page, misnumbered 148.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G¹²  H⁶ (-A1-2, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:1"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN SACRIFICE <hi>By James Barker of Whethampstead P:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pro: 23: 26:</bibl> My ſonne giue me thine heart,</q>
            <q>
               <hi>Sacrificium dei cor contritum ct concuſſum.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>engraved title page featuring two bearded men or prophets gazing upward toward a sun with the Hebrew tetragrammaton or 'Yahweh' at its centre, and another man with a crown and royal robes gazing upward toward a flaming heart</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:yhwh">יהוה</g>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON printed for Humphry Blunden neare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rroyall Exchange in Corne hill</hi> 1630</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull, <hi>Sir</hi> John Garrard, <hi>Baronet;</hi> The bleſſings of this life, and that which is to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe end of mans creation was the ſervice and worſhip of his maker; this (after the fall)
<pb facs="tcp:13677:3"/> began firſt in Sacrifice, whether by mans ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or Gods ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not revealed: certain it is, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods approbation and gracious acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for in the univerſal deluge, when an end of all fleſh was come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: he made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for his ſervice by Sacrifice, in giving order to <hi>Noah</hi> to take into the Arke of every clean beaſt by ſevens. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 2.</p>
            <p>This manner of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:13677:3"/> the light of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon did teach the Gentiles, and Gods owne bleſſed ordinance continued amongſt the Jews, which did ſerve them as it did others, not only as a teſtimony of their obedience to God, and dependance on him but (God ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing) as a Type of that most perfect Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to be offered by Christ on the Croſſe: this once offered, at the laſt put an end to all that went before, and
<pb facs="tcp:13677:4"/> in this one they all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, all Levitical Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, but other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices there are, and theſe the Goſpel ſtill retaines, there in the law, and here in the Goſpel, oblations in <note n="*" place="margin">Oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes enim illic, obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; hic Iraen. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. haereſ. Vali. l. 4. c. 34. p. 429.</note> both: amongſt the people of the Jews, &amp; in the Church of Chriſt, ſacrifices in both: they and wee, the Jew and the Christian agree in this, that God will have Sacrifice; thoſe holy offices of pietie to God and charity to
<pb facs="tcp:13677:4"/> man, are termed Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, ſo that I ſhall not feare to ſay there is a Chriſtian <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> and yet of this of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians (as of that of Jews) how quickly God growes weary, if the Heart be wanting. The heart is the ſalt that ſeaſoneth, and the incenſe that perfumeth the ſacrifice; &amp; makes it an odour of a ſweet ſmell, acceptable and pleaſant unto God: and that our Religious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice may be a Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:13677:5"/> 
               <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> there muſt concurre with an holy action, a devout affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for admit a ſtrict and preciſe obſervation of all circumſtances in the action, if there be a faile in this, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is but lost in that: this is chiefly accepted of God, that ſerving to make a way of diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for man: and for mans ſake, God takes no notice of this without that; diſsembling his knowledge of the inmoſt intentions of the heart,
<pb facs="tcp:13677:5"/> &amp; ſeeming not to know what it is impoſſible he ſhould be ignorant of: untill by ſome outward expreſſions, it be made knowne unto man. It is not then the inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection only that (in the Heart) God calls for; as if he excluded the outward action, but the affectionate action, to doe what is to be done heartily: what is to be done, I ſay! for it is not left arbitrarie to the heart, to chooſe what ſhall be done, or
<pb facs="tcp:13677:6"/> left undone, admitted or omitted: but the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction determined, in the well-managing thereof, is required the ſincere intention, and dearest affectió of the heart: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting alſo the ground as well as the end: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in a duty of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: makes it an effect of heady zeal, not hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die obedience, for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is a Relative: and ever referres to ſome precept, Canon, Rule, decree, conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:13677:6"/> or injunction: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, or at leaſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion whereunto; is that wee terme obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and obedience is better then ſacrifice, or it is the beſt ſacrifice; for hee that obeyeth, makes a ſacrifice of his own heart, and a mans heart is himſelfe <note n="*" place="margin">Per obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam voluntas propria mactatur. Greg. in ult. mor. Aq. 2. 2. Q. 104. ar. 3. reſp.</note> this is the Chriſtian <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> the project of the enſuing diſcourſe: which I have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to expoſe to the view of this cenſorious age: where I muſt not
<pb facs="tcp:13677:7"/> thinke to ſpeed better; then better then my ſelfe have done before me: from the learned I cannot expect that any worke of mine ſhould merrit praiſe: yet doubt not, but at their hands I ſhall find or pitty or pardon: of others, I ſhalbe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as every man ſtands affected; but I paſſe not of their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: ſo long as in conſcience of obedience to God, I ſtrive in my calling to edefie his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:13677:7"/> Church: this is my prime aime: And next to this is to tender un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you ſome token of thankefulneſse for your many favours, <hi>qui be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia invenit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedes invenit,</hi> bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are of a binding na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and a kindnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived obliges an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious nature to requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; but where it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds requital, the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged muſt not come ſhort of acknowledgment, &amp; a verbal acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a poore returne
<pb facs="tcp:13677:8"/> for a reall kindneſſe: 'tis all wee ſchollars can, our wealth is in words., and words are ſwift, no ſooner looſed from the tongue, but lost by the eare; they may touch on the fancy by the way, but vaniſh before they recover the understanding: here then the pen must aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist the tongue, and words once ſpoken, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the more deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate view of the eye: remaine as monuments
<pb facs="tcp:13677:8"/> in the mind; where they admit a review, untill the judictous be fully informed. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the diſadvantage is mine, in stepping from the pulpit, to the preſse; for faults which in <hi>tranſitu,</hi> are not eſpied: at gaſe are eaſily diſcerned; yet here againe is my hope, to meet, as with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent eares, ſo with favourable aſpects: and then patience and connivence will ſalve all defects, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13677:9"/> mine infirmities will be either not ſeene, or not cenſured: Beſides I may ſay with the Orator, <hi>cauſa ago deorum,</hi> I ſpeake in Gods cauſe, not mine owne: and ſo in his name (whoſe cauſe I undertake) may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge acceptance.</p>
            <p>And thus much I dare boldly ſay, I have not by wilfull neglect betrayed the cauſe in hand; but have ſtudied <hi>omnem movere lapidem;</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:13677:9"/> to follow <hi>Solomon</hi> ſo far as my wits would ſerve, in his plea for God: which howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome doe take (which doe uſually miſtake what they doe not understand) I am confident of your favorable acceptance, whom I know ſo far a freind to Learning, and lover of Religion, that what ſo reliſhes of either, finds kind en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment with you.</p>
            <p>Go on, Noble Sir, and ſeaſon the flower
<pb facs="tcp:13677:10"/> of your yeeres with the timely fruits of grace and vertue.</p>
            <p>You want not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements in the way of goodneſſe, nor need you to looke fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then your owne houſe: even to him, that immediatly went before you (your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed * <note place="margin">Sir <hi>John Garrard,</hi> Knight &amp; Baronet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed by his laſt will to the poore of the pariſh of <hi>Whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamſtead</hi> 20. l. <hi>per annum</hi> for ever.</note> Father) who made you the executor of a large legacy to the poore. And left you the heire of a faire e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in Lands and Houſes: and that
<pb facs="tcp:13677:10"/> which is the chiefest ornament of your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion houſe, a most beautifull Chappell, a continuall and viſible <hi>memento,</hi> to put you in mind of your daily dutie to the God of heaven.</p>
            <p>And let it not be thought preſumption in me, that to theſe I have added this as a helpe to your Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to this mine unceſſant prayers for the proſpering of your good beginnings: And
<pb facs="tcp:13677:11"/> for the welfare and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting happineſse of your ſelfe, your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous good Lady and whole familie; ſhall never be wanting, the hearty deſires of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in the ſervice of</hi> CHRIST ſincerely devoted, JAMES BARKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13677:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> CHRISTIAN SACRIFICE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROVERBS 23. 26.</bibl> My Sonne give me thine heart.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He text is briefe, the words few, but full, <note n="*" place="margin">Stilo bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis doctrina uberior, &amp;c Sal. in Ep. Euch. epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopo.</note> for many words need not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt friends: friends in that neer Relation, as <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Sonne:</hi> the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13677:12"/> of Father imports <note place="margin">Pauca ſunt quae man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat ſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutaria &amp;c. Tim. ad ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam cath.</note> Authoritie, the <hi>name of Sonne Obedience:</hi> and where there is Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Veleitie, Power to command, and will to Obey, it is but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and it is done: but this is an intreatie, no command: and it cannot be, that a father (who hath power to command) ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat a <hi>Sonne,</hi> and be ſaid nay: this is the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt requeſt that can be made <hi>[My Sonne give me thine heart]</hi> and yet the hardeſt ſuite, that can be granted, for he that gives his Heart, gives himſelfe, and all hee <note n="*" place="margin">Aq. prima ſecundae. q. 17. art. 9. arg. 1. Idem pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſecundae q. 38. art. 5. reſp. 3.</note> hath.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13677:12"/>
            <p>And now whilſt God calls for the <hi>heart,</hi> let me intreat the eare (your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and attention) that what I ſhall ſpeak, paſſing from the eare to the <hi>heart,</hi> may ſet it in a right temper to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, may fit and diſpoſe it for ſuch a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> as God accepteth: all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sacrifices</hi> without <note place="margin">Non bove mactato Caeleſtia numin a gaudent. Ovid. Ep. 19.</note> this are in vaine, there is none Gods delight, but the <hi>heart,</hi> that he craves; <hi>My ſonne give me thine Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> here ſpeakes, not in his owne name, but in Gods: God by him calls us <hi>ſonnes:</hi> and he for God requires
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13677:13"/> our <hi>Hearts:</hi> It is God, that confers the <hi>Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and God that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the <hi>Dutie:</hi> and he doth it in the ſweeteſt termes of Relation, he comes in love, and ſpeaks in the language of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <q>My ſonne give me thine heart.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>My Sonne,</hi> ſaith God, and in ſaying ſo, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth us what we ſhould ſay: for God in ſuing to us, calling us, <hi>his Sonnes,</hi> teacheth us, in praying to him, to call him <hi>Our Father:</hi> and this ſhould ſerve as a common Rule to all: that none, in any caſe, dare to approach into Gods preſence, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13677:13"/> mention him, without the Addition of his juſt Titles. Reverence, and Humilitie, beſt pleaſes him, and becomes us: In ſome caſes he admittes Boldneſſe, in any caſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtes Rudeneſſe: at the leaſt aford him what he vouchſafeth us, titles of Reſpect; ſeeing wee are taught to call him, <hi>Our Father,</hi> becauſe he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us, <hi>his ſonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſonne,</hi> ſaith God, here is his Intereſt, <hi>Give me thy heart,</hi> there is his Requeſt: And hard it were, that a father ſhould not ſpeed, when he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats his Sonne, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever his ſuit be: the Requeſt is reaſonable,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13677:14"/> and unreaſonable, yea more, unnaturall were that Sonne, to denie that Father any thing, to whom he owes all: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he were too facile, that would entruſt his Heart with every one: It uſes not to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; appropriated for the moſt part, to ſome one, or two, and thoſe deareſt friends: for care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a man is, to whom he imparts his heart: but from a Father (ſuch a one as God) nothing ſhould bee with-held that he would have, thou muſt render up when he requeſts: <hi>My Sonne give me thine heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is Gods ſuite to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13677:14"/> Man, and he preferres his ſuite by way of Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he addes a Preface.</p>
            <p>The Preface is a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle compellation, <hi>My ſonne:</hi> the Tenour of the Petition, <hi>Give me thine heart.</hi> And yet, to call this a Petition is not ſo kindly a Terme: a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to petition his Son: Is it not a Precept ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>jubet non orat pater,</hi> the ſtile of a father, is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative, not optative, and the Father that ſpeakes here is in the ſame moode Biddes, but Beſeeches too. The law, that was imperative on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, preſented God unto us, as a Lord, the Goſpel
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13677:15"/> is more mild &amp; gentle, &amp; reveals him as a father; &amp; when our Lord became our Father, then was the rigour turned into Love, and in love there is a majeſtie, as well as ſweetneſſe, which not only allures, but awes us: If ſtill therefore wee call this a Petition, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogates nothing from Gods Authoritie; his Petition hath the force of a precept, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us with our dutie as well as his deſire; call it then ſtill a Petition, or what elſe you will pleaſe to call it, you ſhall find it hath a double aſpect, to God, and to Man.</p>
            <p>As it Relates to God,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13677:15"/> it points out his love, and Authoritie.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Love,</hi> in own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, for his Sonnes.</p>
            <p>His Authoritie, in vouchſafing to become Our Father.</p>
            <p>As it Relates to man, it points out his Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, his Dutie.</p>
            <p>His Dignitie, to be the Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>His Dutie, to do what becomes Gods Sonne.</p>
            <p>His Love hath exalted us to the dignity of Sons.</p>
            <p>His Authoritie calles for the Dutie of Sonnes.</p>
            <p>And no ſhare ſhall we have in the Dignitie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we performe the Dutie; our Dutie it is, to give God our hearts:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13677:16"/> and then he will give us the Dignitie to become his <hi>Sonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>My Sonne,</hi> It had not beene much to be called <hi>Sonne,</hi> had not God vouchſafed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Father: <hi>Sonne</hi> is but an uſuall and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary complement of a ſuperior to his inferior, <hi>Sonne</hi> ſaith <hi>Abraham to Dives in Hell:</hi> But <hi>My Sonne!</hi> comes from the bowels of a Father, and a title of great Dignitie it is, when God ſpeaks it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Sonne,</hi> ſaith God, and in ſaying ſo, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes his love, and commends our Dignitie: Saint <hi>John</hi> would have all to note this, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13677:16"/> therefore markes it out with an <hi>Ecce. 1. John 3. 1. Behold what manner of love the father hath beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on us, that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God.</hi> It is his love, his free and unmerited love, that hath thus exalted us; It is the Lords doing, and it is marveilous in our eyes, marveilous indeed, for a wretched man to become Gods ſonne: had it been <hi>My ſervant,</hi> it had beene honour enough for man; the greateſt Saints were ambitious of no greater title, there is <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>Servant,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Servant; Pſal.</hi> 105. and <hi>David</hi> in the 116. Pſalme ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13677:17"/> the title, as if he were delighted with it, and tooke pleaſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it; <hi>O Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>truly I am thy ſervant, thy ſervant, and the Sonne of thine hand-maid:</hi> nay the bleſſed Virgin, who had the honor to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Mother of God: yet her humilitie lookes no higher then a ſervant, <hi>ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 1. 38.</note> 
               <hi>ancilla domini,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the hand-maid of the Lord, nay more yet, he that was Lord of all became a ſervant, So by Gods own compellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53. 11. So by his owne profeſſion. 4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 28. and no more in the worlds eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 7. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13677:17"/> it is for any man, to be reckoned amongſt theſe worthies, to be of Gods familie, in any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: but God thinkes it not enough for his Love: It is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>My ſervant,</hi> but <hi>My Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We, that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be accounted ſervants, he hath advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the honour of Sonnes.</p>
            <p>Not <hi>My Servant</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but <hi>My Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, not my friend! this priviledge had <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the father of the faithfull. <hi>Ja.</hi> 2. 23. for his faith: And the ſame is promiſed to Chriſts diſciples, upon condition
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13677:18"/> of their obedience. <hi>Jo.</hi> 15. 14.</p>
            <p>And a great preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere. Diog. do vita, &amp;c. Ego ſenſi animam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam amici mei unam fuiſſe ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam in duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Ang. lib. conf. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ar. lib. 8. 1 th.</note> it is, to be Gods friend, for a friend is <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ego,</hi> a ſecond ſelfe, and <hi>amicorum omnia commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> all things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon amongſt friends, no comfort with-held, no ſecret hid from a friend <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 18. 17. Pet. 1. 4.</note>: yet it is not my freind, but <hi>My Sonne:</hi> for Gods love which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, knows no bounds, but extends to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of kindneſſe, and calls man now, not my Servant, not my Freind only, but my <hi>Sonne.</hi> To be of Gods Court, his <hi>ſervant,</hi> is much: to be of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13677:18"/> his Friend, is much more: but to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the <hi>Sonne</hi> of God, is moſt of all: of this I may ſay, as <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in a caſe not much unlike, <hi>unde hoc mihi:</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 1. 43.</note> whence is this to me, that I ſhould be called the <hi>Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how the Sonne of God? Or what <hi>Sonne</hi> doth God here meane?</p>
            <p>Not his naturall <hi>Son!</hi> ſo is none, but Chriſt as God; he is both <hi>Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitus,</hi> and <hi>unigenitus;</hi> his firſt-begotten, and only-begotten; of the ſame eſſence; conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall, coaeternal, and coaequal with the father;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13677:19"/> begotten by an unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Generation,</hi> which we may adore, cannot ſearch out; for who ſhall declare his Generation. <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. 8.</p>
            <p>Yea Chriſt as man, by grace of <hi>hypoſtatical,</hi> or <hi>perſonall union,</hi> is after a ſpeciall manner, the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> ſo fore-told to be, before he was ſo; <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 32. <hi>That holy thing that ſhall be borne of thee, ſhall be called the Sonne of God.</hi> And ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to be, when he was ſo; <hi>Matth. 3. 17. This is my beloved Sonne, in whom I am well-plea-ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, is none the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> but only
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13677:19"/> he, who both by nature, and the union of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is indeed, the very <hi>Sonne of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are, whom holy <hi>Scripture</hi> hath honoured with this title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> he was ſo, by Creation, the immediate Sonne of God, for God was Father, Mother, God-Father; made him, produced him, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him. <hi>Luke</hi> 3. The Angels they are ſo, made in Gods image, and ſtiled his Sonnes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 6.</p>
            <p>And ſo are Kings, by Gods owne ordination, and ſpecial appointment, the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13677:20"/> 82. 6. <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods, and all of you are Children of the moſt high.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This title thus taken, is a ſingular prerogative, peculiar to ſome ſpecial perſons.</p>
            <p>But here, we will take it more generally, as it is a common title, given by God to all the faithfull. <hi>My Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not by naturall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for ſo is none, but Chriſt as God.</p>
            <p>Not by grace of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall union, for ſo is none, but Chriſt as man. Not by immediate crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for ſo was <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Angels only.</p>
            <p>Nor by Divine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, for ſo are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13677:20"/> Kings and Princes only.</p>
            <p>But by grace, &amp; adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, every true beleever, is truly the Son of God.</p>
            <p>The faithfull by adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are <hi>filij deſignati,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Father for the <hi>Sons</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>Through the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, they are <hi>filii facti,</hi> made the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>And by the laver of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they are <hi>filii ſignati,</hi> ſealed by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>They are firſt deſigned by the Father for heires.</p>
            <p>Then really made and accepted by Chriſt for Coheyres.</p>
            <p>And finally aſſured by the holy Ghoſt of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13677:21"/> undefiled, that fadeth not away, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for them in the heavens.</p>
            <p>Gods <hi>Sonnes</hi> the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are, before they are: ſo in the purpoſe of the <note place="margin">Voſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; ſi nondum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos jam ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natos filios jam credite. Chryſ. Ser. 71. in orat. dominum pag. 306.</note> father, but not ſo in his Delight: they muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by their converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before they can be admitted into Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie: there muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the Fathers purpoſe, the purchaſe of the Sonne, and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the holy Ghoſt: when in the Sonne, and by the Holy Ghoſt, they are made ſuch, as the father purpoſed they ſhould be: then he takes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13677:21"/> delight in them, and ownes them for his Sonnes, and not before: for it is not the fathers Adoption, nor the Sons Redemption, that can priviledge the faithfull from being by nature the children of wrath, even as others. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 3. without righteouſneſſe, holines, Innocencie, and all right to glory; meer carnal men, and ſo by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt ſtill continue, for that which is borne of the fleſh, is fleſh: there <note place="margin">John 3. 6.</note> muſt be a new birth, they muſt be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſo made new Creatures, before they can become the Sonnes of God: and here muſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13677:22"/> not be left out the office of the holy Ghoſt; for as the Sonne of God could not become the Sonne of man, ſo neither can <note place="margin">Luke. 1. 35.</note> the Sonnes of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sonnes of God, without the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall office and operation of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Jo.</hi> 3. this cannot be the worke of fleſh and blood, which naturally produces it's like, carnall, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; nor the worke of man, for <hi>parentes peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores,</hi> our parents are our murtherers, wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive from them the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of ſinne *: and <note place="margin">Non imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſed propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note> with ſin an Obligation to eternall death: and ſo (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin)</hi> wee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13677:22"/> are <hi>damnati antequam nati,</hi> dead in ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alive in the world.</p>
            <p>Mans freedome from this wretched condition, and tranſlation into the glorious libertie of the Sonnes of God, is a worke of Grace, Gods entire worke, ſo Saint <hi>James, Of his owne will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 6. Verbum adveniens aqua dat ei virtutem abluendi. Aq. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>begate he us with the word of Truth. cap. 1. 18. with the waſhing of water by the Word:</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Paul. Eph. 5. 26. Accedit verbum ad elementum &amp; fit Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,</hi> by the power of the word the Element is made a Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And that water whoſe common uſe was to waſh the bodie from filth, now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13677:23"/> ſerves for a holy uſe to clenſe the ſoule from ſin: to this uſe, God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained it, and his Spirit accompanies his owne Ordinance: which (whilſt the eye is fixed upon the ſigne) the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) carries the minde to the conſideration, and ſo on in a ſweet meditation of the thing ſignified (the blood of Chriſt) by that the Baptiſt waſhes the bodie, with this the holy Ghoſt clenſeth the ſoule: and this cleanſing is a changing alſo, <hi>perſona tingitur, &amp; natura muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſen. de Ep. Hom. 3.</note> and this purgation by the blood of Chriſt, is a preparation for the grace of Chriſt, which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13677:23"/> upon is infuſed into the ſoule, ſo St. <hi>Cyprian in expiatum pectus &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum deſuper ſe lumen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundit,</hi> and being then <note place="margin">Cyp. lib. 2. ep. ſecunda. Donato pag. 69. circa ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> infuſed, it giveth to the powers of the ſoule, their firſt diſpoſition unto newneſſe of life; which by frequent acts of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, is wrought into a habit, and ſo is Chriſt formed in us: <hi>tantae mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis erat,</hi> ſuch a do there was, this blood and ſweat it coſt, to Redeeme man from ſlavery and bondage, to repaire the decayes of nature, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the loſt heritage, and to reſtore to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his loſt <hi>Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, brethren,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13677:24"/> you ſee your calling, how <hi>the ſons of Adam</hi> are made the <hi>ſonnes of God,</hi> here's an <hi>Alteration</hi> which the ſpirituall eye may eaſily diſcover.</p>
            <p>Firſt here is a change of our eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: when we were <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> we were reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto God by the blood of his <hi>ſonne,</hi> who by his death overcame death, which we had deſerved; ſuffered for ſinne, which we had committed: fulfilled Gods law, which we had violated: ſatisfied his juſtice, which we had offended; appeaſed his wrath, which we had kindled: recovered his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13677:24"/> favor, and made our peace, and by this means we that were by nature children of wrath, by that Grace and favour which Chriſt hath obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for us at Gods hands are taken in to be the <hi>ſonnes of God:</hi> for ſo well pleaſed was he with the obedience of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>ſonne,</hi> that for his ſake, and at his interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he is pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept us for his ſonnes; thus Chriſt became our baile, and ſurety, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke for us, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe to the meaneſſe of a ſervant, that we might be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the eſtate of <hi>ſonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13677:25"/>
            <p>And that our nature may be fit for that eſtate there's a change of that too; the change of our eſtate is aſcribed to the <note place="margin">Credulitas quae deum ſpiritum proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit de car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li in vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſuſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium vos mutavit. Chryſol. ſer. 71. 2 Pet. 14. Eſt in locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> riches of Chriſts merit: but this of our nature to the grace of his holy ſpirit; this change is not in ſubſtance, but in quality, and ſo in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; though not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the ſpirit of God altereth our nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes us to the Image of Chriſt and makes us partakers of the divine nature, but miſtake not St. <hi>Peter</hi> for by nature he underſtands not the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God which is appropriated onely to the Trinity of perſons
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13677:25"/> and communicated to no man, but the divine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of wiſdome, juſtice, holineſſe, truth, glory and immortallity: and in theſe we have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the Father and with his ſonne <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſo are made wiſe, righteous, holy, mercifull, immortal, and glorious like God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the qualities not equality; our vertues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a ray of his Son, a ſparke of his eternall <note place="margin">Aq. in 2 Pet. 13.</note> fire, a participation of his fulneſſe, he being an inexhauſtible fountaine of grace and goodneſſe, filleth our frayle veſſels, <hi>ſecundum modulum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum,</hi> according to their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13677:26"/> capacity; ſee that what ſoever grace, the holy Ghoſt effectually work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in us, it is firſt ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally in God, and is made ours either by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation or infuſion, our nature is corrupt; I know that in me (ſaith St. <hi>Paul)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ro. 7. 18.</note> dwelleth no good thing: mans goodnes is not inhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent but either impured, or imparted, and ſo when God is pleaſed to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate unto us, his own goodneſſe, there is a change wrought in our nature, new light is put into our minds, new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires into our affections, new obedience into our wils, and a ſweet confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity into all our actions,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13677:26"/> &amp; in this renovation there is no deſtruction, but a converſion; no ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the old ſubſtance, but a generation of new qualityes; there ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines the ſame ſubject, and this alteration of our nature, is a transformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not a tranſubſtantiaton.</p>
            <p>To this new man, there is not wanting a new name; and names are given to expreſſe the nature of things: now no name can ſo fully, and ſo fitly notifie him, who is made partaker of the divine nature, adopted to the inheritance of glory, and immortality, in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as this of Gods ſon:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13677:27"/> here then is a change of our names too, there are no more termes of hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity between God and man, the enmity is now aboliſhed, and all ſuch names as carrie in them ſorrow, ſhame, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery are done away; and a new name that imports comfort, glory, and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is impoſed; and now we are no more enemies but <hi>ſonnes;</hi> now ſurely this is good newes to heare <hi>the father hath found his loſt ſonne:</hi> an Angell is not an able and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent meſſenger, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himſelfe bowes the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and comes downe: <hi>ecce novum behold a new thing upon earth</hi> Eſay 43.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13677:27"/> 19. This is <hi>novum</hi> and <hi>inauditum,</hi> a thing never heard of before: God in the fleſh revealed it; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, God and man reconciled, good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings! <hi>Bleſſed be the peace maker;</hi> God and man made friends, good news welcome be he whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver brings it, his lips are gracious, and his feet beautifull: whoſe heart doth not leape for joy, to heare himſelfe <hi>(by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Father)</hi> called <hi>my Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this new name muſt be attended with a <note place="margin">Chryſ. ſer. 68. in ora. Domi.</note> new life, <hi>qui Dei filium credit actu, vita, moribus honeſtate tanto generi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeat</hi> they that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13677:28"/> themſelves the Sons of God, muſt be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to ſuch honorable compellations: this is a high and a heavenly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and our converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be ſuitable to our calling: <hi>nec degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cyp. ſer. 5. de ora. Domi.</note> 
               <hi>actus noſter a ſpiritu, ut qui coeleſtes &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuales eſſe caepimus, non niſi ſpiritualia &amp; coeleſtia cogitemus, &amp; agamus:</hi> we muſt looke unto the Rock from whence wee are hewne, and beware we degenerate not from that Royall family where into we are admitted, but we who call God, <hi>our Father,</hi> ſhould be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and harmeleſſe, the <hi>ſonnes of God without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13677:28"/> Phil. 2. 15. a godly name and a wicked life agree not: ſinners are hardened, and God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonoured, when he that is called a ſonne of God, behaves himſelfe as a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of ſinne: it is very fit that every ſonne of God ſhould imitate his <note place="margin">Matth. 11.</note> heavenly father: or if he deſire a patern neerer hand; let him learn of his elder brother, <hi>diſcite à me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) learne of me! Frame your lives to his rule, and they wil acquit you, convince men, and pleaſe God; whileſt he ſees his name honored, in your conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, &amp; their convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13677:29"/>
            <p>Old things are paſt, behold all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new: new eſtate, new nature, new name, new life.</p>
            <p>Eſtate happy, the merit of Chriſt hath purchaſed that: nature holy, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt hath ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that: name heavenly, the love of God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed that: life godly, the grace of God hath wrought that: happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, holy nature, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly name, godly life, man is now a <hi>ſonne</hi> by grace not unworthy to be own'd of ſo great a <note place="margin">Prolis tanto non in ficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da parenti.</note> 
               <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length, I have brought you to the height of Gods love,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13677:29"/> and Mans Dignity.</p>
            <p>Gods <hi>Love never</hi> ſo <note place="margin">Et quidem deitatis er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga nos dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio tanta eſt ut ſcire nequeat quid potiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari debeat creatura u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum quod Deus ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit ſervit u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: an quod nos ad ſuae divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis rapuit dignit at em. Pet. Chryſ. ſer. 72.</note> manifeſt, as in making us his <hi>ſonnes,</hi> the utmoſt we could hope for, was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, not for preferment: but to debaſe the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſonne, in making him like us: that he might honor us, in making us like him: is love with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure! which we are as unable to conceive as we are unworthy to receive: the expreſſion is too meane, and low, to ſay it was paternall; a it <note place="margin">Et ſicut om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ut ſcriptum eſt paternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in Coelo &amp; in terris a ſcipſo vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri: fic a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis patris in ſe affectum voluit cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſci &amp; quid dicam patris imo potius plus quam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris. a Sal. di gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. dei lib. 4. pag. 121</note> was more then mothers love, and was, what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is, infinit.</p>
            <p>Man never ſo dignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! who am I? and what is my fathers houſe (ſaith
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13677:30"/> 
               <hi>David)</hi> that I ſhould be Sonne in law to a King? what is fraile man, that he ſhould be exalted to the dignitie <hi>of Gods ſon,</hi> called to the hope, and inveſted with ſome poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of eternall life: what a happineſſe is this, above the reſt of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, who through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and unbeliefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide ſtill in miſery: and I would to God, he would perſwade the hearts of all men, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count this their chiefeſt honour, to be Gods ſons, religion is and ever hath been, the honor and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty too, of kingdomes, familyes, and particular perſons: and this of Gods
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13677:30"/> ſonne, preferred before the moſt glorious titles: It was the Religious boaſt of the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius, malo eſſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. de civi dei l. 5. c. 26.</note> 
               <hi>ecceleſiae quam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put imperij:</hi> and in the moſt magnificent, it is an addition to their honor, to be Gods ſonnes: the greateſt in the world is nothing, if he be leſſe, the meaneſt is enough, if he be ſo much; and ſo much is every true beleever: for to as many as recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to them gave he power to become the ſonnes of God, even to them that believe on his name <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
            <p>How is it then, this priviledge is ſo ſleighted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13677:31"/> and undervalued of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and carnall alliance and kindred ſo much ſtood upon by all: men account their carnall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degrees, and if they can reckon a great man of their houſe how they glory in it, whereas there is greater cauſe of boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, to be of Gods fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then to be deſcended from the loynes of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: for carnall affinity is but tranſitory, it abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not; Kingdomes and families have their periods; and in death there is a diſſolution of al kindred after the fleſh, the mightieſt man alive, muſt one day ſay to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <hi>thou art my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job. 17. 14</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13677:31"/> to the worme, thou <hi>art my Mother, and my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> but our alliance here by faith; death nor the grave hath no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 55</note> and as it is begun on earth by grace in our adoption: ſo ſhall it not be ended but perfected in heaven, by glory in ful fruition: when all the adopted ſonnes ſhall be like the naturall ſonne, and their bodies made conformable to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, according to the mighty working whereby he is able to <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 21.</note> ſubdue all things unto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many</hi> excellent things are ſpoken of you ye <hi>ſons of God!</hi> but what man
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13677:32"/> lives, that dares challenge to himſelf this priviledg? ſeeing every man is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, &amp; if a ſinner, no ſon, for he that is borne of <note place="margin">Ro. 3. 23.</note> God <hi>ſinneth not.</hi> 1. Jo. 5. 18. how <hi>ſinneth not? ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not at all?</hi> God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave any ſuch privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the regenerate (ſaith <hi>Oecumenius)</hi> for the <note place="margin">Oecumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> beſt of Gods Saints ſpeakes in his own name and others. <hi>If we ſay we have no ſinne, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us.</hi> Wee ſinne daily and hourely, the beſt of us, but the beſt of us, ſinne no otherwiſe <note place="margin">1 Jo. 1.</note> then Gods children may ſinne.</p>
            <p>Not totally, with a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13677:32"/> fulneſſe of conſent, <hi>quaſi ad peccatum vacantes,</hi> but over come through infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, with ſtrength of tentation. Nor finally, <hi>ad mortem,</hi> they ſin not that is, ſin not untodeath that ſin, for which the holy Ghoſt hath ſaid thou ſhalt not pray, In all their ſinnes there is ſtill place left for their humiliation and Chriſts Interceſſion, ſo ſtill they are innocent from the great offence, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many leſſer ſins do paſſe them without their knowledge: and many greater ſinnes be committed with their knowledge: yet in the eſcape of thoſe leſſe, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13677:33"/> the committing of theſe greater, they are patients, not Agents, not obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the rule of ſinne, but overmaſtered by the rage of ſinne; here is St. <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe juſt <hi>Ro. 7. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum quod nolo facio,</hi> they ſinne unwillingly, and their unwillingneſſe to ſinne will appeare in their heavineſſe for ſinne when the remembrance is grievous unto them, the burden intolerable, then is the waight not charged on them but laid upon him who hath ſatisfied Gods juſtice, for it, by bearing it on his owne body on the tree, for whoſe ſake, leſſer and unknowne ſinnes <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13677:33"/> abſconduntur</hi> are in charity covered and our greater and well known ſins <hi>poenitentia abluuntur</hi> are by actuall and unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> repentance purged who then ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that juſtifieth! who is he that condemneth? thus the ſons of God they are <hi>ſinners</hi> and no <hi>ſinners. No ſinners!</hi> for being ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith they have not onely a plenary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all ſinnes that are paſſed actually pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by the blood of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but alſo a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from ſinnes to come, effectually promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſpirit of grace.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13677:34"/> But ſinners! in regard of that inherent corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which againſt their wils, doth lead them cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</p>
            <p>For as there is <hi>ſemen gratiae,</hi> a ſeed of <hi>grace,</hi> in the regenerate, which will not ſuffer them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally to ſinne.</p>
            <p>So alſo there is <hi>ſemen peccatia</hi> ſeed of ſin which wil not ſuffer them who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſanctified.</p>
            <p>Chriſt by his death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, hath wholy taken away both <hi>reatum &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciun,</hi> the guilt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal puniſhment of <hi>ſin:</hi> but he hath not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away, but noly weakned Concupiſcience
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13677:34"/> 
               <hi>the root &amp; ſeed of ſin:</hi> which though it be not as grace is, an immortall ſeed, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. yet it is as graceis, a remaining ſeed. 1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 3. 9. rooted and growing in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. It is not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, not a raigning, but a remaining ſinne, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in our fleſh and ſubſtance; muſt have no place in our liking, and affections and ſo it may ſometimes ſomewhat leſſen &amp; abate our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but can never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our happineſſe, whileſt this body of ſin, is kept from raigning in our ſinfull body and brought into ſubjection by the wholſome diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13677:35"/> of ſpirituall morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and then this <hi>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mueles carnis</hi> this throne the fleſh like a Serpent without a ſting hath <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; morſum, non vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> It may ſtir, and bite us; cannot hurt nor kill us: It may bruiſe our heele, but we ſhall bruiſe it's head.</p>
            <p>And thus though we be ſet in the middeſt of evill yet God withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not his tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes from us but his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe, and his truth continually preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 11. And the Lord ſhall deliver me from every evill worke (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> and will preſerve me to his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13677:35"/> kingdome. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 18. Sinne it makes no change in God; it muſt in man, Gods grace in man, makes man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of his ſinne againſt God.</p>
            <p>Mans ſinne againſt God, makes not God Repent of his grace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Man Repents for ſinne, and his repentance ſendes him to the throne of grace, to beg pardon for his ſinne: where we have an advocate <hi>with the father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous,</hi> and he is the propitiation for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God repents not of his grace if man repent
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13677:36"/> of his ſinne, wherefore that wee may continue in his favour, we muſt come before him like the publican into the Temple with contrition in our heartes; and like the loſt ſonne to his Father with confeſſion in our mouths the Phariſie ſtood upon his juſtification, the Chriſtian muſt not, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is the way to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we offend God daily by our ſinnes, yet is he pleaſed againe by our repentance, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents not of his grace but is faithfull and juſt, if we confeſſe he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives. True it is God will not connive at the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13677:36"/> errors of his children, he will be angry with them for their offences, as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his ſonnes; and in his anger viſit their tranſgreſſions with the rod, and their iniquities with ſcourges: but can a Father forget? can a Mother forget? they may, I will not, (ſaith God) <hi>Eſay</hi> 49. 15. he will not take away his loving kindneſſe, nor ſuffer his faithfulneſſe to faile: he hath ſworne by his holineſſe he will not; the foundation of God ſtandeth firme he chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not, but workes a change in man for ſinne that his purpoſe <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to election might</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13677:37"/> 
               <hi>ſtand</hi> * this is his purpoſe <note place="margin">Ro. 9. 11.</note> he hath declared by his promiſe, he hath confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his promiſe by his word, he hath ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his word by his Oath he hath ſealed all theſe with the blood of his <hi>ſon,</hi> he acknowledgeth this his ſeale by the witneſſe of his ſpirit, and his ſpirit aſſureth our ſpirit, that notwithſtanding our many fraylties we are ſtill <hi>ſonnes:</hi> And this he doth not, by immediate revelation, but by an undeniable concluſion drawne from the revealed word: <hi>For if when wee were enemies</hi> we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God by the death of his ſonne:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13677:37"/> much more being recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled we ſhall be ſaved by his life <hi>Ro.</hi> 5. 9. for he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to make interceſſion for us is able to preſerve his own mercies in us.</p>
            <p>Thus God againſt all oppoſition of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> hath exalted us to the dignity of <hi>ſonnes:</hi> and if after this advancement through infirmity, we fall into ſinne: ſhall we account our ſelves no ſonnes becauſe ſinners? If we be truly humbled for our ſins, hartily loath them, deſire to leave them, conſtantly purpoſe to forſake them, &amp; to ſin no more, If we bewail ſins paſt, beware of ſinnes to come ſtrive againſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13677:38"/> Corruptions and by humble confeſſion ſeeke for abſolution, it argues we ar truely penitent, &amp; where God ſees true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, he ſees no ſin: By ſin we go from God, and then he diſclames us: but by repentance we come againe unto him, and whenſoever we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne he receives us. When the prodigall ſaid I will go unto my Father and ſay father I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: the father upbraides not his former Riot, but entertains him as his ſon, this my ſonne was dead but is now alive; though he had loſt the duty of a ſonne, yet had not God loſt the bowels of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13677:38"/> he retained ſtill his fatherly affection, and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ego perdidi quod erat filii, ille qd. patris eſt amiſit. Chry. ſ. 2. 7 de filio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digo idem ſer. 3. de filio prodigo. 1 Pet. 4. 8.</note> 
               <hi>non videt vis amoris</hi> love doth cover a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinnes * it may ſtand therefore with the honor of a father, (ſuch an one as God) to own ſinners for his <hi>ſons,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they have ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heartily for their ſins, and then, with God they that have ſorrowed are as if they had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; But may it ſtand with the piety of a father to leave his children in diſtreſſe, and to expoſe them to want &amp; miſery, If God be their father where is his care over them? his proviſion for them? or can it be that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13677:39"/> the ſonnes of the higheſt ſhould not be ſo wel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for as the fowles of the ayre and foxes of the field? ſometimes it ſo falleth out that God hath a ſtrict hand over his own family, concealing from them the good he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to them, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding from them theſe preſent bleſſings which in a plentifull meaſure he powreth into the lappes of the men of this world; not that he neglecteth his owne whileſt he thus regardeth others, as if he had forgotten to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and ſhut up his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe in diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but by ſome trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in this life, to make
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13677:39"/> their joyes more full, with the aſſured hope of glory and happineſſe in the life to come: nor is he wanting to them in the things of this life, whereof they have the promiſe, and ſhall have the poſſeſſion too, when <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> God ſees it may be for their good; ſo ſtill as a loving father hee ſorts their condition, as may be moſt for their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; ſometimes ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſometimes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging his hand, either in povertie or riches, want or plentie, ſickneſſe or health, adverſitie or proſperitie, they have their ſhare both in the evill and good things
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13677:40"/> of this life, to let them know that thoſe preſent evils are not the greateſt, nor the goods of this life the chiefeſt, but that there are evills to come more to be feared, and future good things more to be deſired, in the patient expectation whereof they muſt be content to endure the want of ſome preſent good, and the ſenſe of ſome preſent evills.</p>
            <p>It ſhould ſuffice them to know that not here, but in heaven, where their Father is, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance is, there muſt their hope be fixed, on that their care placed, and for theſe temporall
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13677:40"/> bleſſings they muſt caſt their care upon God, and depend upon his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly providence, who knows their wants and will ſupplie them, your heavenly Father know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whereof you have need (ſaith Chriſt) and <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> you know it is enough for a father (that is of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, ſuch an one as is our heavenly Father) to know the wants of his Children, his owne goodneſſe will ſupplie whatſoever is needfull or convenient.</p>
            <p>It is not then againſt the honeſtie, and it may well agree with the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of a Father (ſuch an one as God) to owne a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13677:41"/> wretched, if a contrite ſinner, for his beloved Sonne.</p>
            <p>But all this while, this Title ſeems to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Relation to one Sex; ſeems, but doth not: for God, who of the woman requires the dutie, will his Juſtice permit her to be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Dignitie? certainly no! the word is not to be reſtrained to the ſex, but exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſo many of the whole kind, as truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, whether they be male or female; for God is not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he maks no difference of ſexes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, nations, profeſſions, degrees, eſtates or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13677:41"/> of men, but he that is Lord of all, is rich unto all that call upon him, male and female, Jew and Gentile, young and old, rich and poore, prince and people, bond and free, if true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, he ownes them all without difference for his Children.</p>
            <p>And yet there is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference amongſt them, both in reſpect of Gods grace towards them, and his grace in them; they are all beloved, but not equally: and that Gods grace and favour is more to this, then that man, is not from Gods final in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, which is equall and alike to all his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13677:42"/> 
               <hi>[Salvation and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe]</hi> but as men are ſaid to love more, where they conferre more; and to favour moſt, where they receive moſt: ſo God in regard of ſome outward expreſſions of love and favour, is ſaid to love one more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and in regard of mens apprehenſion to ſome, having a greater ſenſe and feeling of his love and favour then others.</p>
            <p>And for his grace that is in them, whether for the qualification of their perſons, or ſalvation of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>If wee ſpeake of the former, ſome are better
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13677:42"/> fitted and enabled for the execution of ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and duties where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by their callings they ſtand charged, wherein he that is moſt faithfull, is moſt highly favoured.</p>
            <p>If we ſpeake of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the more grace God worketh in them, the more gracious hee is ſaid to be towards them: and ſo the ſtronger their faith, the ferventer their love, the more unfained their repentance, the more univerſall their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere their conſcience, the greater his love unto them, the more he is delighted in them, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13677:43"/> ſuch as in his love he hath gifted above their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, he uſually hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth above their fellows; and according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of their graces, is the eminencie of their places.</p>
            <p>And therefore, though all the faithfull be Gods ſonnes, and in relation to him brethren, and he the common Father of all, yet for all this it will not become an inferior to affront his ſuperior with a <hi>jam ſumus ergo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> haile fellow, well met, for his communitie overthrows not that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, which nature, civilitie, and Gods owne ordinance hath made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13677:43"/> man and woman, and one man and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: nor will either ſtate, or Church, or private families, admit ſo abſurd a paritie. To lay all level; no principalitie in the ſtate, no Prelacie in the Church, no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in families, were to ruine all: an inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, which the ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable fore-ſight of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God hath (by his owne bleſſed <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance)</hi> prevented: nor did Chriſt at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (unto whom God committed all rule, and all Authoritie and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) diveſt the Princes of the world of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal and Soveraigne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13677:44"/> wherewith God <note place="margin">Per fidem Chriſti non tollitur or do juſtitiae ſed magis fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur. Aq. prima ſecundae. qu. 104. Art. 6 conc.</note> hath inveſted them, he aboliſhed it not, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it rather.</p>
            <p>And thus though all men be alike in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> made of the ſame mould.</p>
            <p>And all the faithfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> the Sonnes of God.</p>
            <p>Yet the Lord for the ſingular benefit of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hath diſtinguiſhed <note place="margin">How ſon ſer. hab. Oxon. 1602.</note> them in great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and made their wayes and reputations divers: ſome of them he hath bleſſed and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Some he hath ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and appropriated to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13677:44"/> himſelfe, as Prieſts and Prophets.</p>
            <p>Some he advanceth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their brethren, and makes their fathers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren bow downe before them; and others hee leaves in the common rancke: ſome he hath laden with honours, wealth, promotions, and dignities: and others he hath beſtowed in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner callings: thus wiſely hath God ordered the eſtate of this preſent world, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of ſuch variety of parts, begetting a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and bringing a perfect ſoundneſſe and ſweetneſſe to the whole body.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:13677:45"/>
            <p>Where all the ſtrings are of one ſound, there is no muſicke, where all the members are alike, there is no body but a bulke: and even ſo, there is nothing but diſcord and deformitie, where there are not differences of degrees, eſtates and callings of men: and where God hath put a difference, let man doe ſo too, that mans eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation concurring with Gods ordination, every man may be honored and reſpected according to his place and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>The ſtones in a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are not all of one ſyze.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:13677:45"/>
            <p>The veſſels in an houſe not proportioned all for one uſe.</p>
            <p>The members of the body are not all of one faſhion, or for one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>There are many ſtones in a building, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny veſſels in one houſe, many members in one body, and in theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, there is varietie, not Identitie, not many of the ſame, but of divers ſyzes, for divers uſes, of ſeverall faſhions, for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall offices; and this varietie of parts doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get an unitie in the whole, ſo we being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (concludes St. <hi>Paul)</hi> are one body: and in a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13677:46"/> body compoſed of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicitie and varietie of parts, there is more beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie greater ſafety, and this, not only in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <note place="margin">Connexio totius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris unam ſanitatem unam pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chri tudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Tacit. Leo. Ep. 8. cap. 11.</note> body which is man, but in the politicke bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the ſtate; and in the myſticall body, the Church; beautified and ſtrengthened with the ſeverall offices, orders, degrees and callings of men, diverſly qualified, making a diſtinction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men of the ſame Chriſtian profeſſion, for a communitie of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on induces not a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes them rather in peace and good order:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13677:46"/> enjoyning every one (by an Apoſtolical Canon) 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 20. to abide in that calling wherein he is called, propounding no new, but perſwading a more conſcionable uſe of the old * and if there <note place="margin">See Luke cap. 3. verſe 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> be any that hath no cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to get him one, for he that hath no vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is of no Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>There are in the world <hi>viri abſque jugo,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</note> unruly men, who ſtand upon their lawleſſe liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which they miſ-name Chriſtian; untamed hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, whom no pales or walles of law or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline can keepe within the boundes of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13677:47"/> Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, who abhorre that lawfull Authoritie or Chriſtian Charitie ſhould regulate their ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governed libertie. But ſurely this is no privilege of Gods <hi>Sonnes,</hi> a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter it is rather of the ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 19. 22. 1. Cor. 7. 21 1. Pet. 2.</note> for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in one Epiſtle, and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, teach another leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: thus much in effect; that honour, reverence, obedience, and ſervice unto men: may well conſiſt with the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Sonnes of God.</p>
            <p>The freedome Chriſt purchaſed for them is not civil; from the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13677:47"/> of the magiſtrate ſoveraigne or ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, nor naturall from thoſe reſpects and duties which children owe to their parents, wives to their huſbands, &amp;c. But ſpirituall from ſinne and Sathan, death and hell, this and not that is the freedome Chriſt purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> fitly called, the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the Sonnes of God; from which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py libertie, no beleever is excluded: and unto which, the meaneſt hath as good right, as the greateſt; and be mens qualities and degrees, in the world, never ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent God compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13677:48"/> all under one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon motion of <hi>Sonnes,</hi> nor is it any worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that makes a man ever the more favoured with God; for a man to plead his birth, bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, wealth, wit, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, beautie, valour, is more fit for a <hi>Coridon</hi> to his <hi>Alexes,</hi> or a <hi>Phoebus</hi> to his <hi>Daphne,</hi> then a Chriſtian to his God; It is not the proper man, nor the rich man, nor the wittie man, nor the vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant man, nor the learned man, nor the noble man; It is not any of theſe, (though all theſe deſerve a civil reſpect) that God is taken with, his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection pitches on the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13677:48"/> godly man, <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 4. 3.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath choſen to himſelfe the man that is godly: and now let no man diſdaine Gods choyce, how meane ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for whom his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie chooſes, his love ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth to the dignitie of his <hi>Sonne,</hi> and whom his love hath advanced to the Dignitie, from him his authoritie requires the duty of his <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the duty here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed is, to give God his <hi>Heart,</hi> which is the ſecond part of my text, <hi>My Sonne, give me thine heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee be his <hi>Sonnes,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:13677:49"/> God is <hi>our Father,</hi> there is his authoritie over us.</p>
            <p>And if God be our Father, where is his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, there is our duty to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nobilitas ad virtutem obligat,</hi> the greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God hath done us, the greater are our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to him, and therefore as wee have looked up with comfort to the dignitie, ſo now let us looke downe with care to the dutie of Gods ſonnes, which is briefly ſum'd up in two words <hi>Love and Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where <hi>Obedience</hi> is, there is nothing ſo diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult commanded, that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13677:49"/> will not with diligence be attempted.</p>
            <p>And where <hi>Love</hi> is, there is nothing ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious demanded, that will not with cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be tendred, here God tries our Love, by our Obedience, that he may ſee how much wee love him, by that which we will doe for him.</p>
            <p>And againe, he tries the ſinceritie of our <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> by our <hi>Love,</hi> that he may ſee how much we will doe for him by that which we wil cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully give him, and as a pledge both of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> he requires the heart. <hi>My Sonne, give me thine heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:13677:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cor tuum,</hi> thy heart to God, there is the thing required to teſtifie our <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Da mihi, Give mee,</hi> there is the dutie to be performed to expreſſe our <hi>Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The teſtimony of thy Love to God, is thy <hi>Heart</hi> to God. A <hi>Heart,</hi> there is the <hi>quid,</hi> the thing what it is that God requires, <hi>Thine,</hi> there is the <hi>cujus,</hi> the proprietie, whoſe it is.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Heart is the thing God calls for; and what is that? This ſmall piece of fleſh that beates in our mortall bodie? No; that were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire our lives: God will
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13677:50"/> have Mercy and not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: and craves not our life, but our Love; the Heart is the ſeate of Love; that our heavenly Father requires of us his unworthy Children, that we love him.</p>
            <p>And not only our Love, but in calling for the heart, he calls for our feare and ſervice too: for whatſoever the curioſitie of ſome Philoſophers have determined to the contrary, the heart is the ſeate of all the affections and paſſions: the Gall, Liver and Spleene, give the occaſion to ſtirre them up, but in the heart they are ſeated: the Heart is the Metropolis
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13677:51"/> of the ſoule: and often taken for the ſoule with all her faculties.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Heart is <note place="margin">Omnis hona diſpoſitio corporis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duci dat quodam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ad cor ficut ad principium corporaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> motionum Aq. 1, 2. q. 38. art. 5 reſp. ad 3. arg. Vide Aq. 1 2. q. 17. art. 9 arg. 1. &amp; 2.</note> the firſt mover of all the Externall actions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very member worketh according to the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, inclination and will of the Heart; It liveth firſt, and dyeth laſt, and therefore firſt, and laſt, and for all, give God the heart, for that is all: All the faculties of the ſoule; all the members of the body, attend the Heart and follow it: the Heart goes before and drawes the whole man after it.</p>
            <p>And this is Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light <hi>the whole man:</hi> he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13677:51"/> loves <hi>Integrity;</hi> and in calling for the heart he requires every part: thy head to know him, thy tongue to confeſſe him, thine eyes to obſerve him, thine eares to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto him, thy lips to praiſe him, thy hands by good workes to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him, thy knees to bow before him, and thy feet to ſtand in his Courts. God is not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at all, where any part is withheld from him, or devoted to any other beſides him, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and integrity are individuall companions, If true devotion lodge in the <hi>heart,</hi> humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence will ſhine in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13677:52"/> part. So ſings <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> Pſal. 84. 2. <hi>Cor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; caro mea exultave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. &amp;c. My heart</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly <hi>and my fleſh</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly have rejoyced in the living God.</p>
            <p>Thus the whole man muſt apply it ſelfe to the worſhip of God, the outward, aſwell as the inward man: by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 16 Oecum in locum.</note> man, the learned * underſtand the body: the inward man by St. <hi>Peter</hi> is expounded to be the hidden man of the <hi>heart:</hi> that, aſwell as this, this in private, that in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, this with inward and ſpirituall, that with outward and corporall worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:13677:52"/>
            <p>In private then and in thine owne Chamber, commune with thine owne <hi>heart,</hi> the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods ſpirit and thine own is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            <p>But in publik in Gods preſence Chamber the <hi>Temple;</hi> it ſufficeth not, except the <hi>Church</hi> may ſee too: that all may ſee and beare witneſſe that God is in you of a truth, and this cannot be, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept mens externall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do ſhew forth their internall affections. The <hi>heart</hi> that is unſcrutable to man but * <hi>gentis cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hirom. Geſtus eſt ſermo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Cic. de Orat. lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>vox animi,</hi> the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward carriage of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is a faire teſtimonie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13677:53"/> of the inward diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of thy mind:</hi> and then is diſcovered what the heart thinketh, by that which the body acteth: for <hi>grace</hi> in the <hi>heart</hi> is the light of the body, and this light muſt ſhine before men, that they may ſee aſwell as God: And that men may reape the good, &amp; God receive the glory, Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inſpirations, and mens holy deſires ſhould empty themſelves here, that the Church may outwardly teſtifie, what <note place="margin">Ad ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mentis humanae in Deum Aq. pri. ſe. queſt. 102. art. 3.</note> inwardly each man ſhould be by ſuch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip, as might betoken the Majeſty of God, beſeeme the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13677:53"/> of Religion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the celeſtiall impreſſions in the minds of men. <note place="margin">Idem. 2. 2. q. 92. Art. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The performance of all Religious ſervices re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect God and man, to pleaſe him, and edifie them: and ſo muſt be equally poyſed with the two theologicall vertues <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Charity, Faith</hi> towards God, and <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> towards men, without <hi>faith,</hi> it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, and <hi>cordi cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur</hi> man believeth with the heart, it is the heart that ſeaſoneth our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and faith that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth the heart, directs it to the true object, and in the right end of pure Religion.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13677:54"/>
            <p>And as faith ſeeketh to pleaſe God: ſo <hi>charity</hi> to approve it ſelf before men, and <hi>charity</hi> in the performance of a duty unto God hath reſpect unto the benefit of man too.</p>
            <p>God ſees faith in the internall devotion of the <hi>Heart,</hi> and therewith he is well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>Men ſee <hi>charity</hi> in the externall carriage of the body, and therewith they are edified.</p>
            <p>God calls for that, by <hi>Solomon</hi> in my text, <hi>My ſonne give me thine heart,</hi> and he cals for this by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in another text, to preſent your bodyes ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 1</note> 
               <hi>ſacrifice</hi> &amp;c. and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13677:54"/> then concludes, and not til then your devotion to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, your reaſonable ſervice and good reaſon there is, God ſhould be ſerved both in body, and ſoule; for at the firſt he made both, and he once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed both, he day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerveth both, and finally ſaveth both: and therefore glorifie him in both.</p>
            <p>And thus the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an offers that <hi>Holocauſt</hi> to God in ſubſtance and truth, which the <hi>Jewes</hi> did offer in type and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, making his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches into the houſe of God with <hi>Davids</hi> hymn in his mouth: <hi>Introibo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 66. 13.</note>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13677:55"/> 
               <hi>in domum tuam Holoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis,</hi> I will go into thy houſe, with burnt-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: but now in Gods houſe there is no uſe of fire, unleſſe it be the Metaphorical fire of true zeale, for true zeale is Gods fire, of which St. <note place="margin">Aug. in pſ. 66. alias 65</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> thus, <hi>totum meum conſumit ignis tuus, nihil mei remaneat, totum ſit tibi</hi> Let thy holy fire of zeale, O Lord, conſume me wholy, and make me thine in every part; all thine, and then is all his when he hath the heart, for as the powers of it are inclined ſo are the parts of the body moved: there is a league of amity betwene them,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13677:55"/> like that betwene <hi>Ruth</hi> and <hi>Naomi</hi> the body like <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi,</hi> cleaving to the ſoule and ſaying; intreat me <hi>not to leave thee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 1. 16 John 1. 16 Anima in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectiva quamvis ſit una ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam tamen propter ſui perfectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eſt mul tiplex in virtute &amp; ideo ad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſas ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digit diver ſis diſpoſitio nibus in par tibus corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris cui poni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Aq. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma q. 76. art. 5. riſp. ad 3. arg.</note> or toreturn from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after thee, for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt <hi>I</hi> will go, and where thou lodgeſt I will lodge, thy people ſhalbe my people, and thy God, my God; or as his ſouldiers did to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuah</hi> all that thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt us we will do and whether thou ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt us we will go, for albeit the ſoule in eſſence be one, yet to the perfection of it, there are divers faculties: and for the ſeverall ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of theſe faculties,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13677:56"/> there muſt needs be an anſwerable diſpoſition in the partes of the body to which it is united: for as the fire firſt kindleth the fuell, and that being kindled nouriſheth the fire: and as the body firſt warmeth the clothes, and then they returne a reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall heat to the body; ſo the heart firſt diſpoſeth the parts of the body, and theſe partes fitly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">In divino cultu ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quibus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralibus uti ut eis quaſi ſignis quibuſdam mens homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis excite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituales actus quib. Deo conjun gitur Aq. 2. 2. queſt. 81. art. 7. Eccleſiam piis quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam coere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moni is ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantibus ritibus &amp; inſtitutis tanquam ſponſam or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natam viro ſuo decora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Cornal. Agrippa de van. ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiarum cap. 6.</note> affect the heart, and make devotion in the heart, like the fire in the <hi>Sanctuary, a flame</hi> that goes not out.</p>
            <p>And even experience it ſelfe teacheth us, how merveilouſly outward forme and ſolemnity in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13677:56"/> Gods ſervice doth helpe weakeneſſe and inbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in us; perſwading the will, inciting the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and making ſome impreſſions of further knowledge in the mind, winging our thoughts, holding up the heart in her devotions, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtength and vigour to ſuch motions which are otherwiſe apt to lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and conclude in a lazie wiſh: but the parts of the body fitly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed keepes up the heart till Gods wil be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and mans duty diſcharged.</p>
            <p>True it is God hath ſometimes excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13677:57"/> but then when it hath been alone, when the people drew neere him with their lippes, and their hearts were farre from him. But when or where <note n="*" place="margin">Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cultum non repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus imo etiam ab omnibus pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is requirit nec enim tantum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo colere debemus, ſed etiam coram ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtari, &amp;c. Calvin. ap. Mart. in Matth. 15. 8. Jo. 4. 22.</note> ſhew me, was ever God offended with the humble, lowly and reverend geſture of the body in his ſervice, or where did he ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne outward Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, when it was joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with inward ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, never did hee open his mouth againſt the uſe of that, but the want of this. The true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſhall worſhip God in Spirit and truth (ſaith the Sonne of God) but how in truth, if not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13677:57"/> in body, as well as inwardly in heart and ſpirit, God is robbed of his worſhip, when either is with-held, and when both are not exhibited Gods houſe is made of a houſe of Prayer, a den of theeves.</p>
            <p>And the ſame ſpirit that by the Son of God commends inward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, doth by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and thoſe no mean ones neither, (his Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> and <note place="margin">Eſay 45. Ro. 14. 12.</note> his Apoſtle <hi>Paul)</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand outward worſhip. <hi>As I live (ſaith the Lord) every knee ſhall bow unto me, and every tongue ſhall confeſſe to God.</hi> And thus what God hath
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13677:58"/> joyned together in his precept, let not us ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in our practiſe, ſerve God with the inward worſhip of the <hi>Heart,</hi> and with the outward worſhip of the body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: open impietie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with this, and ſecret hypocriſie is glad to heare of that; the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite is all for outward pietie, the profane for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſinceritie.</p>
            <p>But it is neither the pretence of inward ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie that can juſtifie outward impietie: nor a ſhew of outward pietie that will excuſe inward hypocriſie: be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, <hi>Deus non illudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> God is not mocked,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13677:58"/> but ſitteth in heaven to laugh all thoſe to ſcorne, who either by hidden projects, or open practiſe caſt ſcornes upon Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhip.</p>
            <p>If any man pretend inward ſinceritie, let him ſhew it in outward works of pietie, men judge of the inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, by the outward action. Or if any ſtand upon outward pietie before men, let them ſhew it in their inward ſinceritie before God, who judges the outward action by the inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and wee know (ô Lord) that thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is according to right: A mans workes
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13677:59"/> may paſſe currant, and ſeeme right in <hi>foro ſoli,</hi> in the judgment of men, when as they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo in <hi>foro poli,</hi> in the ſight of God: for God ſees not as man ſees; he looks not at the outward appearance, but at the heart: In a dutie performed, men ſee all well, but what ſaith God, men cry out a Saint, God ſaies a ſinner: heaven and earth doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes agree in their judgements: It is our daily prayer, that it may be in earth as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that it may be, and therefore is not: the grant of this petition wee muſt preſſe, that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13677:59"/> Gods will be done on earth, as it is in heaven, ſolemnly and ſinceerely too, that there be an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie on earth, and this uniformitie, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to heaven, for what ſhall it availe a man, though the world applaud him, if God and his owne heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him: It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> advice, <hi>Gal. 3. 23. Whatſoever ye doe, doe it hartily, as to the Lord, and not unto men.</hi> And yet wee muſt not conceit, as if God ſimply condemned the outward action: nay he approves it ſo farre as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently good: he only diſlikes this, that it is not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13677:60"/> done heartily, with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere intention, which God finds often wanting in thoſe immediate du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his worſhip and ſervice: as prayer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out attention, hearing without meditation, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting without contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Almes and no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, knowledg with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out devotion, zeal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcretion, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance without reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and theſe deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are rather in their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, then the act, which ſo far as good apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God approves, but diſlikes them, &amp; diſlikes them for this: becauſe they did <hi>(bonum non be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne)</hi> that which was good:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13677:60"/> good for the matter, but not done in that good &amp; ſeemly manner, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to that good end which crowneth all our workes.</p>
            <p>For it is not ſo much the <hi>quid,</hi> what is done, though that muſt be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable: and wee muſt have a warrant for what we doe, or elſe we ſinne in what we doe. Nor is it the <hi>quî,</hi> the manner of doing, and yet wee muſt have a Rule and Canon for that too, or elſe wee diſobey in what we doe; and ſo with <hi>Martha</hi> make choice of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer part, for Obedience is better then ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>quid</hi> then, we
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13677:61"/> muſt looke up to God, who points us to his word, and that gives di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the matter of Gods ſervice.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>quî,</hi> wee muſt have recourſe to the Church, who by vertue of that grand Canon of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> hath power to determine our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 40</note> for the manner of Gods worſhip, in all the circumſtances thereof; both for perſons, places, and times, for every ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, poſture and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for preaching, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring, praying, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, hearing, receiving, ſinging, confeſſing, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and to diſpoſe of all other accidentals accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13677:61"/> to <hi>decency</hi> and good order. And now ſuppoſe for the matter, all done as God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: for the manner, all done decently and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly as the Church hath enjoyned: yet as our Saviour ſaid to the man in the Goſpell <hi>unum tibi deeſt,</hi> there is ſomething wanting, the intention of the heart that muſt be right too, for it is that which maketh religious exerciſes performed, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of obedience; Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> limits all to this <hi>quantum intendis tantum facis,</hi> when a man in his intention ſwerves from that true end to which his worke in hand ſhould
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13677:62"/> tend he looſes his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the action; for men to be of the Phariſes cut, of whom St. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, oculi hominum timor eorum, oculi homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num amor eorum,</hi> fearing nothing but the cenſure of men, loving nothing but the praiſe of men, this baſe popularity, is the bane of true piety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia fiant,</hi> let all be done that God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: <hi>omnia decenter &amp; ordine,</hi> all decently and in order as the Church hath enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia cordicitûs &amp; ex animo</hi> al heartily with a pure intention, in the feare of God, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13677:62"/> of holy Church: and ſo all will be done as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would have all done: <hi>Omnia ad edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem &amp; omnia ad</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 26 1 C. 10. 31.</note> 
               <hi>gloriam Dei:</hi> All to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and all to the glory of God.</p>
            <p>It is the heart then, that addes a goodneſſe to all we ſay: and gives perfection to all we doe in Gods ſervice; were mens words like <hi>Herods, divina oracula</hi> the voyce of God and not of men: their workes like the Phariſies <hi>admiranda ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacula</hi> admired of all: It availeth nothing at al; <note place="margin">Act. 12. 22</note> if their hearts in the meane time be <hi>Daemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum receptacula</hi> replete
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13677:63"/> with guile and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Good words without the <hi>Heart,</hi> is plaine flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and good workes without the <hi>Heart,</hi> is <hi>groſſe hypocriſie;</hi> now God is not ſo weake, to be dilighted with flatering words: nor ſo unwiſe to be deceived with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall workes: when therefore we draw neere unto God it muſt be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with a true <hi>Heart,</hi> voyd of flattery <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 22</note> and hypocriſie: he is not delighted with that, nor can he be deceived with this: he requireth truth in the inward parts the heart is his deſire and delight too.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:13677:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Sonne give me thine Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not the <hi>Heca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombs</hi> of the Gentiles, nor yet the <hi>Holocauſtes</hi> of the Jewes, but the <hi>Heart</hi> of the Chriſtian is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice God accepteth <hi>the heart</hi> is the <hi>quid</hi> the thing required but the <hi>cujus</hi> whoſe it is, comes now to be ſcanned the text ſaith, <hi>tuum,</hi> thine heart, and thine, lookes abroade and relates unto man, It is <hi>cor hominis</hi> the heart of a man, not <hi>cor belluinum</hi> a bruitiſh and barbarous <hi>heart</hi> the ſavage and undomitable <hi>heart</hi> of a beaſt, but the corrigible gentle and pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able heart of a man, ſuch
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13677:64"/> a heart that may be wrought upon, not an obdurate ſtubborne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent heart, this is no fit preſent for God, who hath regard to him that is poore, &amp; of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at his word. It muſt be <hi>cor humanum thine heart, O man.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſay 66. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And is mans <hi>heart</hi> ſo pretious a Jewell that God ſhould become a ſuitor for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> telleth us, that <note place="margin">Gen. 6 7.</note> God ſeeth every imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of mans <hi>heart,</hi> that it is onely evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>heart</hi> is deceitfull above <note place="margin">Jer. 17. 19.</note>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:13677:64"/> all things, and deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked, who can know it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath taught, that out of the <hi>heart</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 19.</note> evill thoughts, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers adulteris &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Shall ſuch a heart be offered unto God, or will the ſearcher of the heart accept of ſuch an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? he is a God of purer eyes then to behold ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, neither ſhall any <note place="margin">Matth: 5.</note> wickedneſſe dwell with him, (our Saviour ſaith) the pure in <hi>heart</hi> ſhal only ſee God; take the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <note place="margin">Jam. 4. 8.</note> counſell therefore; and purifie the <hi>heart</hi> and that it may be purified, deal with it as with gold, melt it, or if thou canſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13677:65"/> not melt it, breake it; for a broken and a contrite <note place="margin">Pſ. 51. 17</note> 
               <hi>heart</hi> O Lord thou wilt not deſpiſe.</p>
            <p>It is (you have heard) <hi>cor hominis</hi> the heart of a man that muſt be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but not the phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>heart</hi> of the proud <hi>man</hi> full of hypocriſy, nor the wanton heart of the laſcivious <hi>man</hi> full of vanity, nor the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous <hi>heart</hi> of the worldly <hi>man</hi> full of iniquity, nor the hereticall <hi>heart</hi> of the malitious <hi>man</hi> full of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy: but the contrite and broken <hi>heart</hi> of the penitent man full of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: <hi>ad hunc reſpiciam</hi> (ſaith God) to this <hi>man</hi> will I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <note place="margin">Eſay 66. 2.</note>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:13677:65"/> and to his offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>tuum</hi> in my text looks neerer home, and points out the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner here, and the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner here is a <hi>ſonne.</hi> It is <hi>cor filii, thine heart my Sonne,</hi> and a ſonnes heart is a loving and dutyfull heart: the ſervant doth his duty aſwell as the ſonne but he for feare, this for love, that conſtrained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this moſt willingly, his obedience is not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinary, and ariſes from love not hire; as the dog ſerves his Maſter <hi>pro oſſe &amp; offa:</hi> for a bone and a bite, but as a ſonne his Father in reverence and love: It is the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13677:66"/> and tender heart of a ſonne that is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, <hi>thine heart, my Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt <hi>my ſon! thine heart, tuum;</hi> that is <hi>propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cor,</hi> thine own, in thine own power, and in thine owne poſſeſſion, it muſt be thus thine: If lent to vanity thou muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call it, if bound to ſin thou muſt releaſe it, if ſold to Sathan thou muſt redeem it, <hi>thine heart</hi> muſt be releaſed from ſinne; recalled from vanity, and Sathan diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed; and then, when it is purged and purified, ſet at liberty and enlarged, and ſo made thine, when none
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13677:66"/> other hath any intereſt in it, or can lay any claim unto it, but that it is thine own; not enthral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Sathans tentations, not intangled in carnall luſts, not diſtracted with worldly cares, when it is no more the <hi>heart of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> but of a ſonne; then ſuch it is as God would have: <hi>thine own heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe <hi>thine heart my Sonne,</hi> that is <hi>cor unicum &amp; ſimplix,</hi> one ſingle heart: for one man hath but one <hi>heart: Solomon</hi> tels us the fool hath none heart <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 16. But <hi>David</hi> the Father of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſets out the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a heart and a heart <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12. 2. in Saint
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13677:67"/> 
               <hi>Hieroms</hi> tranſlation: with a double heart in our al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed tranſlation the context tels us whom he meanes <hi>he that doth one thing</hi> and intendeth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſaith one thing but thinketh another, this <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sent. Theog</note> man the ſcripture cryes out upon <hi>voe duplici cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di:</hi> nor will God have any thing to do with him: the Prophet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers him <hi>Pſal</hi> 55. 21. by his faire tongue and falſe heart, the words of his mouth are ſmoother then butter, having warre in his heart, <hi>Judas</hi> like, he uſhers in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with a kiſſe, and like to <hi>Joab</hi> makes a ſmiling face and a friendly ſalute
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:13677:67"/> the prologue to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſtabbe, the double hearted man is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and uncertaine for when his mouth ſpeakes ſafety, his <hi>heart</hi> ſpeakes ruine; and there is one that underſtandes the language of the <hi>heart:</hi> &amp; for that any man hath ſaid in his heart, that is, hath entertained envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and malicious thoughts againſt the godly, trecherous and rebellious thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Church or State, he muſt be anſwerable to God for theſe thoughts, for even theſe thoughts come within the compaſſe of the lawes tranſgreſſion; of Gods
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13677:68"/> law, but not of mans, mans law puniſhes onely the notorious: Gods law takes notice of the heart: And ſo God <note place="margin">Pſal. 5. 9.</note> knowes though men do not; the thoughts of the <hi>heart:</hi> that their inward parts are very wickednes albeit the mouth be muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that it dare not ſpeak it: and the hands bound that they cannot effect it for when he ſpeakes his thought it is ruine to the godly, <hi>when ſhall he dye and his name periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſtruction to the Church, down with it, down with it, even to the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſolation to the State, come and let us make Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem a heape of ſtones.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:13677:68"/>
            <p>Thus the malicious or double-hearted man, like <note place="margin">Eſay 5: 8. Pſ. 36. 4. Pſ. 139. 3.</note> the covetous, would be alone upon the earth, for miſchiefe ever delights to be ſolitary; never conſidering that God is about his bed, and about his paths, and eſpieth out all his wayes: God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth his thoughts afarre off, nor is there a word in his tongue, but loe, O Lord thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it altogether: God ſees, and abhorres to ſee a falſe <hi>Heart under a faire</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Simulata ſanctitas duplex ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas.</note> 
               <hi>tongue,</hi> for this with God is a double ſinne: the Heart is his delight, but it is <hi>ſimplex cor,</hi> a ſingle heart, a Heart without guile and hypocriſie, the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13677:69"/> faithfull are called <hi>Doves,</hi> and innocencie and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity are the properties of a <hi>Dove:</hi> and yet for protection from injurie, for the prevention of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and preſervation of pietie; It is beſt to take our Saviours counſell, and joyne to the Doves <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 16.</note> heart the Serpents head: for harmleſſe ſimplicitie, and Chriſtian policy may well ſtand together: for Chriſtian policy is to true Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſugar to fruit, keeps &amp; preſerves the ſent &amp; taſte: and often cauſes that they who diſtaſte them raw and uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, ſweetly to reliſh them thus fairely orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: thy heart for God
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13677:69"/> then, and although it be <hi>Corſapiens,</hi> let it be <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex,</hi> a wiſe and warie, but a ſingle harmleſſe heart; and the good Lord pardon every one that prepareth his heart to ſeek God, the Lord God of his fathers, though he be not clenſed according to the purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Sanctuary. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. 19.</p>
            <p>Laſtly here is one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie more of the Heart, it muſt be <hi>totum</hi> or <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum,</hi> thy whole Heart, like the true mother of <note place="margin">1 King. 14. 8. 2 King. 23. 25. 2 Chron. 22. 9. 2. Chron. 31. 21.</note> the child, his fatherly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection will not admit a diviſion: It was the commendation of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Joſiah, Jehoſophat,</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:13677:70"/> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> in the old Teſtament, that they ſought the Lord with all their heart: and it is Chriſts commandement in the new Teſtament, that we love him with all our Heart: for to love God with all the Heart, is in effect as much as to give him the Heart: but not the whole heart, there is ſomething more in the heart then Love, for Diſcretion, Percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Conſideration and Meditation, are affirmed of the Heart: And all theſe are acts of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and God is ſaid to bleſſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> &amp; to give him an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding heart. 1. <hi>K.</hi> 3. 12.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13677:70"/> &amp; the Heart is ſaid to be the ſeat ofwiſdom, ſo that God in calling for the <hi>heart,</hi> requires the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to know him, as well as the affections to love him, and he hath not the whole heart, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he have both; I will not diſpute whether of the two is more uſefull for us, or acceptable to him; hee requires both, we can lack neither, nor can the one well ſubſiſt without the other, and the heart is not perfect where either is wanting; Knowledge begetteth Love, &amp; Love encreaſeth knowledge, if knowledge preceed not, it is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inſtinct, not Love,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13677:71"/> for how can we love God before wee know him; It is a true Rule, <note place="margin">Inviſa dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaquam. Aug. apud Amb. de ſpiera. ſer. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ignoti nulla cupido,</hi> no knowledge, no love: It is the knowledge of the worth of the object of our love that ſpurres on the affections; the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding goes before, and there followeth the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the will, that diſcernes; this chooſes: the underſtanding, by diſcourſe, examines the object, and having found it <hi>[utile &amp; jucundum]</hi> right and good: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it to the will, which readily embraceth it under thoſe termes, <note place="margin">1. Jo. 4. 7.</note> and ſo the better wee
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13677:71"/> know God, the more we love him, and the more we love him the better we know him, <hi>Love and be wiſe then</hi> the Apoſtle makes uſe of one word to ſignifie both <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Col. 3. 2. by this manner of ſpeech giving us to underſtand that our love to God muſt not be an irregular paſſion, but a well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered affection: for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from whence the word commeth ſignifieth the mind or underſtanding, to teach us that our love muſt not be directly bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out from the will but muſt paſſe by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: and have there allowance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13677:72"/> it break forth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt you muſt labor to know God, and that knowledge will reforme your love, love him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely and that love will inform your knowledge, for knowledge without love is vaine, knowledge <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 2.</note> puffeth up, it is love that edifieth: had a man all knowledge if he have not love it is nothing, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 2</note> the holy Scripture ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth it above its fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, gives the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence to it, determins all in it, as the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all vertues: and it is love that moves them all to their proper Acts: that maketh faith believe hope rely, patience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13677:72"/> temperance ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, humility ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>Yea in love there are two paſſions, <hi>deſire and feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A deſire to pleaſe God in all things.</p>
            <p>A feare to offend him in any thing.</p>
            <p>The feare to offend God begets an awfull <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence</hi> to his dreadfull name.</p>
            <p>The deſire to pleaſe him incites to a cheerfull obedience of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, and the triall of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of our duty, &amp; the duty here enjoyned is, <hi>Give.</hi> God that gives all requires ſomething not
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13677:73"/> by way of requitall or compenſation, for ſo man hath nothing to render him for all his benefits: but by way of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or gratulation, and ſo it is fit, very fit, that ſome preſent be tendered and given to him, that hath given all to us and loe what it is, the heart that muſt be given, <hi>My Sonne give me thine heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhall we then call this <hi>donum,</hi> and not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum,</hi> our free gift, and not our bounden duty. Is it not he, that hath made us and not we our ſelves: and ſo he may challenge our hearts as his owne <hi>jure creationis</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:13677:73"/> by the right of creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the maker of them. It is he that hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and bought us at a deare rate the life of his <hi>Sonne: pretio empti eſtis magno</hi> ſaith St <hi>Paul</hi> and thus the heart it his <hi>jure redemptionis</hi> by right of purchaſe as the Saviour and redeemer of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in Baptiſme we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted ourſelves wholy to him and ſo <hi>jure pacti</hi> by right of ſale or covenant the heart is his; and yet he ſaith <hi>give,</hi> as if it were ours, whereas he may juſtly take it as his owne, may; but will not: he that made thee without thee, will not ſave thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, and though
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13677:74"/> Salvation be the free gift of God and a worke of grace, yet there muſt concurre the act of mans will who if he would be ſaved muſt worke out his owne <hi>Salvation</hi> with feare and trembling. It is certaine, God can by violence take the heart of man but he will have it freely <hi>given:</hi> drawing by faire meanes the will of <note place="margin">Qui fecit te ſine te no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſalvabit te ſine te Auſt</note> the fleſh into conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the law of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>But doth not he who here ſaith give, in the 4 chapter of this book verſe twenty three, ſay keepe thy heart with all dilligence, and how can a man do both <hi>give</hi> and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13677:74"/> 
               <hi>keepe,</hi> for by a gift there is <hi>tranſitus rei ad alium,</hi> a thing is made over to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: And yet in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, we know, the ſame thing may be both <hi>given</hi> and <hi>kept</hi> when a man makes over his right to another retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the uſe to himſelfe for a time: but God in this caſe wil admit of no ſuch reſervation nor wil he be content to accept of the <hi>heart</hi> in reverſion, he will have it in preſent, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry actuall and reall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and when once <note place="margin">Hieroms tranſ.</note> the <hi>heart</hi> by faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is conſecrated to God, he bids keep it, not from him, but for him, the word is <hi>ſerva</hi> *
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13677:75"/> ſave it for him, ſell it not to another: <hi>omni cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ſerva,</hi> with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of keepe: with wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, faſting, praying: with watching, that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than with his tentations enſnare it not, with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, that the fleſh with it's luſts entangle it not; with praying, that the world with it's cares di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract it not: and thus to keep it, is abſolutely to give it.</p>
            <p>Or if thou wilt not abſolutely give it, yet <hi>da mutuò</hi> lend it God, bring it to his houſe, and let him have the uſe of it here, It may be the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Gods houſe may ſo affect thine <hi>heart,</hi> that
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13677:75"/> what at firſt thou didſt barely lend, afterward thou wilt moſt cherefully give: And even preſent thy ſelfe before thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <note place="margin">Plautus in. Tri.</note> father with the ſonne in the comedy: <hi>pater adſum impera quod vis ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tibi ero in mora. Father command me what thou wilt,</hi> loe here I am ready to do thy will and this the heavenly father kindly accepts from his <note place="margin">Terent. in And.</note> ſonne, and with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the comedy commendes him for it; <hi>facis ut te decet cum iſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoc quod poſtulo, impero cum gratia.</hi> Or if thou will not freely give yet lend it God whileſt thou art here: remember that
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:13677:76"/> God is in this place though you know it not and when you come into this place it is with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to meete your God, or elſe you might aſwell keepe away, and meet him you muſt not without your heart, that is his <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and his charge is like that of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> to his brethren <hi>Gen.</hi> 43. you ſhall not ſee my face except your brother be with you, let not us have occaſion to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as <hi>Iſaac</hi> to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Gen. 22. 7.</note> 
               <hi>behold the fire and the wood,</hi> but where is the Lambe for a burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, here are your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes your eares to heare, your knees to bow, your
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:13677:76"/> tongues to give praiſe (and well it were if in this place theſe parts were ſo well diſpoſed) but where is the heart for a burnt offering: Oh let not your hearts be in your fields in your hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in your ſhoppes, in your coffers, running af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter covetouſneſſe and vanity when your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes are in the Church, let no coveteous volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, ambitious or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious thoughts divert your heart from Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice but lend him your <hi>harts</hi> whilſt here you are.</p>
            <p>Or if it will not be lent yet <hi>da pretio</hi> ſell it him, he is ſo taken with the <hi>heart,</hi> that he will have
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13677:77"/> it at any rate; the bleſſings of this life, &amp; that which is to come, glory &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality; yea if it coſt the glorious kingdome of heaven, &amp; the death of Gods naturall ſon ſtake but the heart &amp; take all.</p>
            <p>Or if thou wilt not <hi>dare pretio,</hi> ſell it him, nor give it him, nor lend it him: if neither the exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of preſent bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, nor the promiſe of future happines can win the heart to the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Gods holy name nor'to the obedience of his heavenly will, why then your blood will be upon your owne heads, God hath done his part your deſtruction is from
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13677:77"/> your ſelves, he would, but ye would not, <hi>nay quoties voluit</hi> how often would he, alluring by his mercyes perſwading by his Miniſters who in his name and in his ſtead do ſecond <hi>Salomon</hi> in his ſuite for the <hi>heart My ſon give me &amp;c.</hi> And muſt God for all this go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Heart, for us (it ſeemes) he may, but for his own names ſake he will not: for, as he alone is the ſearcher and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the heart, ſo he alone can rule it: turne and alter it: as it ſeemeth beſt to his godly wiſdom: yet he compels it not: perſwads it rather, &amp; ſo winning: are his perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13677:78"/> that they have the force of a law, &amp; the moſt <note place="margin">Volunt as non cogit ur</note> ſtony &amp; ſtout heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand out, when he bids yeeld; &amp; ſtill it is not compulſion but perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>monendo &amp; movendo</hi> with ſuch motions &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition he works upon it, <hi>non compellendo ſed ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter inclinando,</hi> not violently compelling but ſweetly inclining it, for when the <hi>ſtiffeneſſe</hi> and ſtubbornneſſe of the Heart rejecteth kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he works it by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions &amp; puniſheth not in anger, but in love: and <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 19.</note> ſo his puniſhments are chaſtiſements, not judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>levamina non gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vamina,</hi> gracious not
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13677:78"/> grievous or if for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they be ſomewhat grievous (as no affliction for the time is joyous) yet in the event they are gracious, working the Heart to Obedience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it to Gods will, and making it pliable to yeeld when God calls <hi>Give me thine heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if for all this mens Hearts be ſo ſtiffe that they will not yeeld, then God brings them into great extremities, and preſſes them with manifold neceſſities, that (like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove to the Arke) in the want and weakeneſſe of other meanes they may fly to him who is <hi>totius ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatis
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13677:79"/> remedium</hi> a ſure ſupply of all wants, and yet neceſſities and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mityes may breake the heart not bend it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Gods holy ſpirit be with it. It is the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and lively worker of grace in the heart, mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and framing it to ſuch a temper, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes obedient to the heavenly calling: and when once the Heart is thus wonne then ever after the leaſt ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods heavenly pleaſure is a forcible command, and every motion from him is a powerfull motive to us, reſigning our hearts moſt willingly: when
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13677:79"/> he requeſts ſo lovingly <hi>My ſonne, give me thine heart.</hi> And now at laſt I am come to the laſt word of mytext, <hi>Mee, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi, mi fili,</hi> to me my ſon, <hi>mihi patri,</hi> to me thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thy <hi>heart to me:</hi> and here wee have the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of his demand, which ſeems at firſt ſight to croſſe the law of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whoſe rule is, <hi>ſuum cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> to give every man his owne, how then ſhall wee think Gods demand equall and juſt, which runs in this ſtile, <hi>tuum mihi?</hi> thine to me.</p>
            <p>Amongſt men indeed, where the Relation is no higher then betweene
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13677:80"/> neighbour and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the law of equitie is violated, when one man uſurps that which is anothers, for Gods law forbids every man to covet any thing that is his neighbours, nor can conveniencie grant a diſpenſation for the breach of Gods law.</p>
            <p>But betwixt God and <note place="margin">Quod homo habet Dei ac domini ſui munus eſt. ac per hoc in his quae offeruntur ab homine homo non ſuum red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſuum recipit. Tim. ad Cath. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ele ſiam. l. 1. pag. 366.</note> man, the caſe is altered, for God in juſtice may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that which is thine to be given to him, for nothing thou haſt is ſo thine, but that it is Gods alſo, of all thou haſt, thou haſt only the uſe; the right is Gods, thou the poſſeſſor, hee the owner, and ſo in deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:13677:80"/> what is thine, hee calls but for his owne, nor is it againſt equitie for God to demand what is thine, ſeeing what is thine in keeping, is his indeed; but againſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for man to refuſe to give what in right hee hath no reaſon to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from the true own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: and therefore from God to man, <hi>da mihi tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> give me that which is thine, is an equall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>But God hath no need of any thing a man hath, all the beaſts of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt are his, and ſo are the cattell of a thouſand hills, &amp;c. His Ocean needeth not our drop,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:13677:81"/> his Alſufficiencie mans wealth: miſtake not, his requeſt is not to ſupplie his owne neceſſitie, but firſt that we ſhould make ſome expreſſions of our dutie, and by preſenting him with part of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, thereby to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <note place="margin">Nemini du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium eſt, quod ea quae dei dono ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepimus ad dei cultum referre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beamus. Tim. ad Eccl. cath. lib. 1.</note> wee hold all from him.</p>
            <p>Secondly to ſhew our obedience to his bleſſed ordinance, which enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to honour the Lord with our ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Thirdly for his poore childrens ſake, whoſe caſe hee makes his owne.</p>
            <p>And ſo if God ſtand in need of nothing man can give, yet Chriſt
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:13677:81"/> doth, not <hi>Chriſtus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, ſed Chriſtus myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not the perſon of Chriſt, for God hath put all things in ſubjection under his feete, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted him to be Lord of all.</p>
            <p>But the bodie of Chriſt <note place="margin">Totus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus eſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus. Auſt.</note> his Church, that labours under many wants, and God expects the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Church ſhould be ſupplied of that which is thine, his Temples beautified, his Miniſters maintained, his poore members relieved, and what is given to any of theſe God acknowledges as given to him, ſo that when God becomes a
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:13677:82"/> ſuiter unto man, it is not for himſelfe, but for his Church, hee makes his Churches caſe his owne, and when a man gives to his Church, he offers to God, the time was when the forwardneſſe of the giver prevented all ſuit: and then ſo much was given, that now God needs not to turne beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar for his Church, give him that which is his owne, that which the pietie of former times hath endowed his ſpouſe with, and then ſhee may ſay as <hi>Eſau</hi> to <hi>Jacob, I have enough my brother, keep that thou haſt unto thy ſelfe. Gen.</hi> 33.</p>
            <p>But yet I have not
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:13677:82"/> done with <hi>tuum mihi,</hi> thy goods, thy body, thy life, <hi>omne tuum,</hi> all thou haſt to God, when by that thou haſt, thou mayſt doe him ſervice, keepe nothing back.</p>
            <p>But above all that is thine, thine heart to God: any thing elſe thou haſt God commends into thine hand, &amp; gives thee libertie to diſpoſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corpus terrae,</hi> thy body <note place="margin">Terram ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra tegat, daemon, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat, mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus res ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat ſpiritus aſtra petat.</note> to the earth, earth it is, and to earth it muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, commend it therefore to the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated bed of duſt, to ſleepe with it's fathers, untill by the laſt trumpe it be awakened to a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſurrection.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:13677:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Bona amicis,</hi> leave thy goods to thy freinds, to the Saints upon earth, and ſuch as excell in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and forget not to tranſport a part before thee in pious and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table uſes, remember thy freinds in heaven as well as thy kindred upon earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peccatum Dia bolo,</hi> thy ſinne to Sathan, hee was the firſt ſuggeſter of it, and a daily tempter to it, ſtop his mouth with a <hi>tolle quod tuum eſt &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> let him gaine nought from thee but thy ſinne, that is his, and bid him take his owne and be packing, but <hi>Cor mihi,</hi> thy heart for God, wee
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:13677:83"/> muſt breath out our ſoules with <hi>David, In manus tuas Domine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo ſpiritum meum,</hi> into thy hands, O Lord, I commend my ſpirit, all other parts at times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient may labour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the things of this life: but <hi>ſur ſum corda,</hi> the Heart muſt never looke ſo low heaven is <note place="margin">Col. 3. 2.</note> it's hope, and her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation muſt be as high as her hope, where her fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt, and from this fellowſhip ſhe muſt not ſtray: when the eyes are abroad in the world, the heart muſt ſtill be fixed in heaven,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13677:84"/> and let nothing remove it from that ſtation, keep it there, and it keeps the whole man upright: whilſt the Heart is devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, there is no violence, briberie or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice in the hand; no luſt, covetouſneſſe or envie in the eye: the eare is not open to vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or blaſphemie: there is no Idolatry in the knee, no bitterneſſe or falſhood in the tongue, no guile in the lippes, no impietie to God, no injurie to man, and this is the bleſſed fruit of the hearts devotion: thy Heart to God then.</p>
            <p>Other Competitors there are for the Heart.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:13677:84"/>
            <p>The world cries <hi>Cor mihi,</hi> give me thine heart and thou ſhalt have wealth and honors.</p>
            <p>The fleſh cries, Give it me, and thou ſhalt have eaſe and pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Give it me (ſaith Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than) and thou ſhalt have all theſe, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the world, and the pleaſures of the fleſh, give him but the heart, and he will give all, how comes hee thus munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, <hi>Paracelfus</hi> tels us, he is but a beggarly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and therefore let him not delude the heart with vaine hopes, or deceive it with falſe ſhewes, hee promiſes all; but can give none; <note place="margin">Matth. 4.</note>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:13677:85"/> ſuppoſe him able to make his promiſe good, yet all hee promiſes, even the whole world, is not a valuable price for the heart, and will any man be ſo adventerouſly foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, as to ſell upon truſt, at an under rate; and to Sathan too; ſo bad a pay-maſter, the verieſt huckſter in the world; Give it him! it is loſt for ever, but in Gods kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it is ſure enough: and this is not all the heart gaines by being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to God, not ſafety <note place="margin">Domine quia feciſti nos ad te irrequiet u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt cor do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcat in te. Aug.</note> only, but ſatietie too, he fils the heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents it to the full, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on earth with his grace, and crowning it
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13677:85"/> in heaven with his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, even for his Chriſts <note place="margin">Jo. 1. 14.</note> ſake, whoſe is the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of grace and glory; to whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Spirit, three Perſons, but one LORD GOD Almighty, Be aſcribed all might, majeſtie and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:86"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:86"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>Jan. 26. 1638.</date>
               <signed>GUIL. BRAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:87"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13677:87"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Good Reader, with thy pen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the faults eſcaped in the preſſe thus,</hi> ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page. 8. line 5. blot out the. p. 12. l. 20. blot out 4. p. 30. l. 1. read ſo. p. 33. l. 20. r. qui ſe Dei filium. p. 37. l. 6. blot out for. p. 38. l. 18. Sonne. p. 40. l. 5. r. recount. p. 43. l. 7. blot out is not. p. 46. l. 23. r. only, p. 48. l. 3. r. ſtimulus. p. 52. l. 1. blot out is. p. 58. l. 2. r. theſe. p. 60. l. 20. 1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 62. l. 12. r. too: l. 13. blot,. p. 64. l. 19. r. this. p. 67. 19. r. ranke. p. 74. l. 2. r. notion. p. 83. l. 20. r. geſtus. p. 84. l. 2. r. the. p. 85. 116. r. corde. p. 87 l. 4. adde: p. 88. l. 1. r. Holocauitis. p. 94. l. 10. r. gald.</p>
            <p>In the margent: p. 20. r. dominicam. p. 28. r. ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam. p. 36. r. proles. p. 37. r. voluit. p. 55. r. eſt non. p. 80. r. redun iat. p. 89. r. indiget, cui unitur. p. 112. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
